Guide to the Donald Clifford Gallup Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- February 2000 Acquisition, 1918-1964; 10; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  - T. S. Eliot Papers
    - Manuscripts
      - "A Brief Treatise on the Criticism of Poetry", circa 1920
        Purchased G. F. Sims, 1955.
        Autograph ink manuscript: 4 leaves, 23cm.
        See: letter 170 (to Monro, [March? 1920]), to which manuscript was probably enclosure. First portion of essay only.
      - Draft of message sent to a cultural congress at Bad Ems, 1951
        Purchased by C. A. Stonehill Inc. at Christie's sale, 1952 Jun 11.
        Autograph pencil manuscript, signed: 3 leaves, 26cm.
        Includes letter 371 to Stephen Spender, 23 Jan 1952, to which manuscript was enclosure.
      - "Lines for Cuscuscaraway and Mirza Murad Ali Beg", 1933 February 24
        Purchased Gotham Book Mart, Feb 1937.
        Autograph ink manuscript: 1 leaf. 14 1/2 cm. Signed and inscribed.
        "A fair copy made for John and Helen Cournos, 24 Feb 1933 (the day after Eliot lectured in Sprague Hall on "The English Poets as Letter writers," when I saw him for the first time)."
      - "The Old Gumbie Cat", undated
        Purchased Seven Gables Bookshop, 1961
        Typescript (original): 1 leaf. 28cm. Prepared for (by?) Mrs. John Carroll Perkins. Varies from published text.
      - "A Personal Anthology", 1948
        Gift of Mrs. Henry W. Eliot, Jr., 1948.
        Typescript (original): 5 leaves. With a few manuscript corrections.
      - The Use of Poetry and the Use of Criticism, 1933; 2
        Purchased Seven Gables Bookshop, ca. 1950
        a. Galley proofs, with manuscript editorial markings by Harvard University Press readers, for American edition: 49 numb. leaves.
        b. Setting typescript (original) for 3 preliminary pages and page 26.
        c. Page proof for English edition, with author's manuscript corrections and additions for the American edition: 160pp.
        d. Page proof for American edition, with author's manuscript corrections and answers to proofreader's queries: [vii], 149pp.
        e. Page proof for American edition, with manuscript editorial markings by Harvard University Press readers, who have copied author's corrections and additions from 29c: ca. [vii], 149pp.
        f. Page proof of reset pages mostly in two states.
      - The Use of Poetry and the Use of Criticism, 1933; 4 (Box 22)
      - "A Valedictory. Forbidding Mourning: To the Lady of the House", 1935
        Includes: Typescript (original): 2 leaves. 25 1/2cm. Signed, with manuscript corrections, and inscribed to Mrs. John Carroll Perkins, 28 Sept 1935. Unpublished. Purchased Seven Gables Bookshop, June 1961.
        Prepared by Mrs. Perkins. Signed, with manuscript corrections, and inscribed by the author for Mrs. Perkins, [Petersham, N. H.] 18 Jul 1946. Purchased Goodspeed's, Dec 1972
        Pencil copy (probably in the hand of Mrs. Perkins): 3 leaves. 22 1/2cm. With ink corrections and annotations (probably also by Mrs. Perkins) and indication of lines omitted in reading by Eliot at Petersham, 18 July 1946. Purchased Seven Gables Bookshop, 1961.
        Another typescript: 5 leaves. 14cm. Prepared by some member of the Perkins family for reading. (n.d.) Purchased Seven Gables Bookshop, 1961.
        Ink copy. 4 pages, 21cm. In envelope inscribed in pencil: "As read by T. S. E. at Petersham, Mass., for E B P's garden lecture July 18, 1946", and in ink: "Garden Poem by T. S. Eliot, 1935."
    - BBC Talks
      Typescripts from B.B.C. files (1949) as follows, in chronological order:
      - "The Elizabethan Grub Street: Nashe", 1929 June 18
        Typescript (carbon): 9 leaves. 33cm.
        At head of title: Six Types of Tudor Prose: II. Printed Listener (19 Jun 1929)-C287.
      - "Philosophic Prose: Bacon", 1929 June 25
        Typescript (carbon): 9 leaves. 33cm. Printed Listener (26 Jun 1929)-C288
      - "The Popular Preacher: Donne", 1929 July 2
        Printed Listener (3 Jul 1929) with title: The Prose of the Preacher: The Sermons of Donne-C291.
      - "The Literature of Travel", 1929 July 9
        Printed Listener (10 July 1929) as "Elizabethan Travellers' Tales"- C292.
      - "The Literature of Biography", 1929 July 16
        Typescript (carbon): 8 leaves. 33cm.
        Printed Listener (17 Jul 1929)-C293-as "The Tudor Biographers."
      - "17th Century Poetry", 1930 March 7
        Typescript (carbon): 11 leaves. 33cm.
        Printed Listener (12 March 1930)-C302
      - "Seventeenth Century Poetry III. The Devotional Poets", 1930 March 21
        Typescript (original): 10 leaves. 33cm. With ms corrections by author on page 1.
        Printed Listener (26 March 1930) as "The Devotional Poets of the Seventeenth Century: Donne, Herbert, Crashaw"-C304
      - "Seventeenth Century Prose IV. Vaughan, Traherne, Marveil", 1930 March 28
        Printed, revised? Listener (2 April 1930) as "Mystic and Politician as Poet: Vaughan, Traherne, Marvell, Milton"-C306
      - "Seventeenth Century Prose V.- From Cowley to Dryden", 1930 April 4
        Typescript (carbon): 10 leaves. 33 cm.
        Printed Listener: (9 April 1930) as "The Minor Metaphysicals: From Cowley to Dryden"-C307
      - "Seventeenth Century Prose. VI. John Dryden", 1930 April 11
        Typescript (carbon): 10 leaves. 33cm.
        At head of title: Seventeenth Century Poetry VI. Printed Listener (16 April 1930)-C308
      - "John Dryden (1) The Poet", 1931 April 12
        Printed Listener (15 April 1931)-C317
      - "John Dryden (2) The Dramatist", 1931 April 19
        Printed Listener (22 April 1931)-C318
      - "The Modern Dilemma XXIII. Religion and Science: A Phantom Dilemma", 1932 March 20
        Typescript (carbon and original): 1 leaf, 11 numb. leaves, 27cm. With ms. corrections and additions by the author, pp. 1,2,3,4,5,6,8,9,10,11.
        Printed Listener (23 Mar 1932)-C331
      - "The European Debt to Roman Literature", 1944 June 19
        Typescript (carbon): 3 leaves. 33cm.
        Unpublished?
      - "East Coker", 1946 March 17; 2
        Typescript (Mimeographed): 6 leaves. 33cm. As read by author.
      - "Books and People: Charles Williams", 1946 October
        Typescript (carbon): 6 leaves. 33cm.
        Printed, revised? as "The Significance of Charles Williams"? Listener (19 Dec 1946)-C521.
      - "John Milton", 1947 March 26
        Typescript (original): 14 leaves. 33cm.
        Made from recording at British Academy. Published as Milton (London [1947])- A49-and in Proceedings of the British Academy (1951).
    - Correspondence
      - 1. Typed letter, signed, to Denys Val Baker: London. One page, 26cm., 1945 March 6
        On Eliot's bibliography (making reference to the 1937 Catalogue.)
        Purchased Bertram Rota Ltd., 1958
      - Letters to Arnold Bennett
        Purchased Stonehill, 1936.
        - 2. Autograph letter, signed: London. Two pages, 18cm., 1918 December 14
          With Bennett's manuscript note: "Ans./17-12-18". Thanking him for writing letter of recommendation for commission.
          (With a typed copy of Bennett's letter, made by DCG from the original at Harvard.)
          Letters 260-61.
        - 3. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1924 July 13
          With Bennett's manuscript note: "Ans./16.7.24". Requesting an appointment to discuss a "scheme" he has "in view" [i. e. Sweeney Agonistes ]. (With Bennett's retained typed carbon of his secretary's reply.)
        - 4. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1924 August 10
          Thanking him for his letter. With manuscript note by Bennett "remind me of this."
        - 5. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1924 October 8
          Asking for an appointment and saying that he has "five or six typed pages of dialogue, and a very brief scenario" to submit to him.
          With manuscript note in margin by TSE "say nine o'clock?" (With Bennett's retained carbon of his reply, 9 Oct 1924.)
        - 6. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 18cm., 1924 October 11
          Agreeing to come on Tuesday at 9:00.
        - 7. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1924 October 23
          Saying that he is reconstructing the play in accordance with all Bennett's suggestions, and thanking him for his help.
        - 8. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1925 April 18
          With Bennett's manuscript note: "Ans./21-4-25."
          Explaining that he has been ill but that he will finish the play "next winter" and wants to bring it to him for criticism again. Asks to publish something of Bennett's in the Criterion.
        - 9. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1925 April 21
          With Bennett's manuscript note: "Ans./23-4-25."
          Regretting that he cannot accept invitation to lunch but asking to come see him at some other time.
        - 10. Typed letter, signed on Eliot's behalf by his secretary, I. P. Fassett: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1925 April 24
          Agreeing to come on Monday at 5:30 PM. With manuscript note by Bennett "mark this up".
        - 11. Telegram in unidentified hand: London. Two pages, 13 1/2cm., 1925 April 27
          Regretting relapse prevents him from keeping appointment.
        - 12. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm. (With Bennett's retained typed carbon of his reply, 29 April 1925.), 1925 April 28
          Apologizing and asking for new appointment.
        - 13. Typed letter, signed: London. One page 26cm., 1925 June 9
          With Bennett's manuscript note: "Ans./12-6-25".
          Asking him to dine.
        - 14. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26cm., [no year] April 1
          Enclosing typed carbon of letter to the (London) Evening Standard, 29 April 1927, two pages, with reference to Bennett's notice in the Standard of The Enemy. The letter to Bennett has a manuscript note explaining that he probably won't send the letter to the Standard but wants Bennett to see it. (With Bennett's retained typed carbon of his reply, 3 June 1927. Two leaves.)
        - 15. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1927 June 25
          Thanking him for his letter and requesting an appointment to discuss his contributing to the Criterion. (With Bennett's retained typed carbon of his reply, 7 July 1927.)
        - 16. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1927 July 25
          Accepting his "Florentine Journal" for the Criterion. With manuscript draft of Bennett's reply on verso and recto. (Typed letter signed by Eliot's secretary I. P. Fassett, 9 July 1927 precedes, acknowledging receipt of Bennett's typescript.) (With Bennett's retained typed carbon of his reply, 27 July 1927, and a typed copy of Bennett's subsequent letter of 1 Sept. 1927.)
        - 17. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1927 September 5
          Concerning publication of "Florentine Journal" in Criterion and commenting on George Sturt. (With Bennett's retained typed carbon of his reply, 6 Sept. 1927.)
        - 18. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1927 September 7
          Thanking him for his letter. (With Bennett's retained typed carbon of his reply, 19 Sept 1927.)
        - 19. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1927 October 14
          On publication of "Florentine Journal." (Preceded by typed letter signed by Eliot's secretary I. P. Fassett, 20 Sept 1927, on the same subject.) (With typed letter, signed, from the Monthly Criterion, 17 Oct 1927, sending proof. With manuscript note by Bennett concerning proof.)
      - 20. Autograph letter, signed, to Van Wyck Brooks: London. Two pages, 23cm., 1920 August 9
        With reference to their days at Harvard together, the Freeman, book-reviewing, and his work, and asking to be remembered to Maxwell Perkins and for Tom Thomas's address.
        Purchased Henry W. Wenning (who bought it from Mrs. Brooks), 1964.
        Letters, 397.
      - 21. Typed letter, signed, to Kate Buss: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1924 March 5
        Agreeing to sign her copy of Prufrock.
        Purchased Stonehill, 1941.
      - Letters to Godfrey Childe
        Purchased Stonehill, 1937.
        - 22. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 25 1/2cm., 1936 February 18
          On his (i.e., Eliot's) manuscripts.
        - 23. Typed letter, signed: London. Two pages, 25 1/2cm., 1936 February 26
          On his manuscripts and enclosing four specimen pages of Murder in the Cathedral. (With photocopies - supplied by Valerie Eliot - of Eliot's retained carbons of three additional letters to Childe: typed letter from secretary, 10 March 1936; typed letter from Eliot, 17 March 1936; typed letter from Eliot, 10 Oct 1946.)
        - 23a. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 23 1/2cm., 1936 March 4
          With manuscript corrections.
      - Letters to R. Cobden-Sanderson
        "Purchased by Bertram Rota Ltd. at Sotheby's sale of 11 May 1964, and sold to me June 1964. On the Criterion ."
        - 24. Typed letter, signed: London. Two pages, 26 1/2cm., 1921 October 2
        - 25. Autograph post card, signed: London. One page, 11 1/2cm., 1921 October 9
        - 26. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 21cm. Letters, 503., 1922 January 24
        - 27. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 21cm, Letters, 506., 1922 January 29
        - 28. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 21cm., 1922 January 30
        - 29. Autograph letter, signed: London, "Wednesday". One page, 21cm., undated
        - 30. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm. Letters, 511., 1922 March 13
        - 31. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 20 1/2cm., 1922 June 12
        - 32. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1922 June 27
          With manuscript additions by Eliot. Letters, 534.
        - 33. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 July 13
          Enclosing typed copy for advance circular with manuscript additions in an unidentified hand (Cobden-Sanderson's?). Letters, 541.
        - 34. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 July 18
          With manuscript addition by Eliot. Enclosing copy for stationery with manuscript additions in unidentified hand ("Submit revise." possibly in Eliot's hand.)
        - 35. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 August 9
          Letters, 556-57.
        - 36. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 August 31
          With manuscript addition by Eliot. Letters, 568-69.
        - 37. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 September 10
          Letters, 569.
        - 38. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 September 26
          Signed with initials.
        - 39. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 September 27
          Letters, 574.
        - 40. Autograph letter, signed: London. Two pages, 27cm., 1922 September 28
          Letters, 575.
        - 41. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 October 1
          With two manuscript corrections by Eliot. Letters, 575-76.
        - 42. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 October 3
          Letters, 576.
        - 43. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 October 13
          Signed with initials. Letters, 581.
        - 44. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 October 15
        - 45. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 October 16
          Letters, 582.
        - 46. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 October 18
          With manuscript postscript by Eliot. Letters, 584-85.
        - 47. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 November 8
          With manuscript postscript by Eliot. Letters, 593-94.
        - 48. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 November 12
          With manuscript postscript by Eliot.
        - 49. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 December 26
        - 50. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1922 December 31
          With manuscript postscript by Eliot. Letters, 612.
        - 51. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1923 January 9
        - 52. Autograph letter, signed: [London?]. One page, 27cm., 1923 January 19
        - 53. Autograph letter, signed: [London?]. One page, 27cm., 1923 January 21
        - 54. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1923 February 14
        - 55. Autograph letter, signed: London. Two pages, 23cm., 1923 April 15
        - 56. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1923 May 24
        - 57. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1923 May 7
          Signed with initials. With a manuscript correction and manuscript postscript by Eliot.
        - 58. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1923 May 28
        - 59. Autograph letter, signed: Fishbourne. One page, 27cm., 1923 June 3
        - 60. Autograph letter, signed: Fishbourne. One page, 23cm., 1923 June 9
          Signed with initials. Followed by typed letter, signed, from Richard Aldington, 17 Jun [1923].
        - 61. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1923 July 1
        - 62. Autograph letter, signed: [London?]. One page, 26cm., 1923 July 5
          Signed with initials. Enclosing manuscript draft for circular concerning the first volume of the Criterion, three pages, 22 1/2cm.
        - 63. Autograph letter, signed: London. Two pages, 26 1/2cm., 1923 July 6
        - 64. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1923 July 15
        - 65. Autograph post card, signed: Fishbourne. One page, 12cm., 1923 August 5
        - 66. Autograph letter, signed: London. Two pages, 27cm., 1923 August 8
        - 67. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1923 August 22
        - 68. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1923 September 14
          Signed with initials. Followed by sheet prepared by Richard Aldington of "Payments to contributors to The Criterion...Oct 1923" with an address supplied in manuscript by Eliot and initialled by him twice and dated 27 Sept 1923.
        - 69. Autograph note unsigned on typed letter, signed, to Eliot from Cobden-Sanderson. One page, 27cm., 1923 September 28
        - 70. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1923 October 11
        - 71. Autograph letter, signed: [London?]. One page, 27cm., 1923 October 15
        - 72. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 27cm., 1923 November 20
        - 73. Autograph letter, signed: [London?]. One page, 20 1/2cm., 1923 December 3
          Requesting payment to Wyndham Lewis.
        - 74. Autograph letter, signed: London. One page, 18cm., 1923 December 9
        - 75. Autograph letter, signed: [London]. One page, 25 1/2cm., 1923 December 13
          Signed with initials. Followed by draft circular letter (in hand of Richard Aldington?) with two manuscript notes by Aldington, one page, 26cm.
          With three autograph letters, signed, to Cobden-Sanderson from Mark Wardle (translator of Valéry's Le Serpent ) and one from Arthur B. Baruch.
      - 76. Typed letter, signed, to Guido Eeckels: London. One page, 20 1/2cm., 1952 February 5
        Thanking him for sending the printed report of an interview. With an autograph letter, signed, from Eeckels to Jacob Schwartz, Brussels, 19 June 1954, giving the background of the letters. Two leaves.
        Purchased from Jacob Schwartz, 1954.
      - Letters to Henry W. Eliot, Jr.
        Gift of Henry W. Eliot, Jr., 1939, and 1940.
        - 77. Typed letter, signed: London. Two pages, 26cm., 1938 December 23
          On Christmas presents for his family and The Family Reunion.
        - 78. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26cm., 1939 March 28
          On The Family Reunion, mentioning copy inscribed for DCG and with reference to Louis MacNeice.
        - 79. Typed letter, signed, to Ford Madox Ford: London. Two pages, 26 1/2cm., 1923 October 11
          Edited by Ford for publication in the first issue of the Transatlantic Review (Jan 1924). Purchased House of Books Ltd., 1948.
        - 80. Typed letter, signed, to Donald Friede: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1930 September 22
          Concerning Poems (1919). Purchased for DCG from Macy catalogue by Stonehill, 1934.
      - Letters to Donald Gallup
        Received from T. S. Eliot. For Christmas cards, see end of list.
        - 81. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26cm., 1936 February 21 (Box 23)
          Answering questions about his books.
        - 82. Typed letter, signed: London. Two pages, 26cm., 1936 November 18
          Answering bibliographical questions.
        - 83. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 25 1/2cm., 1937 January 6
          On the Gallup collection.
        - 84. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 25 1/2cm., 1937 August 17
          "Asking me to tea."
        - 85. Typed letter, signed: London. Two pages, 25 1/2cm., 1938 September 8
          On the copy of Prufrock presented to Susan Jepson.
        - 86. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 25 1/2cm., 1942 November 27
          "Regretting not having seen me in London on Thanksgiving Day and promising to send me Little Gidding ."
        - 87. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 25 1/2cm., 1942 December 9
          "Refusing my offer of Prufrock ."
        - 88. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 25 1/2cm., 1945 November 16
          Giving permission to have the Bodleian manuscripts filmed.
        - 89. Typed telegram: London. One page, 12 1/2cm., 1945 December 11
          Suggesting an appointment.
        - 90. Typed letter, signed: New York. One page, 28cm., 1946 June 17
          Concerning possible meeting.
        - 91. Typed letter, signed: London. Two pages, 21cm., 1946 October 7
          On bibliographical matters.
        - 92. Typed letter, signed: London. Two pages, 21cm., 1946 November 1
          Answering bibliographical queries.
        - 93. Typed letter, signed: London. Two pages, 21cm., 1946 November 26
        - 94. Typed letter, signed: Cambridge, Mass. 27cm., 1947 May 13
          Arrangements for New Haven visit. With manuscript postscript by Eliot.
        - 95. Typed letter, signed: Cambridge, Mass. 27cm., 1947 May 14
        - 96. Typed telegram: Washington, D. C. 15cm., 1947 May 24
          Is eager to talk with W. S. Lewis.
        - 97. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 20 1/2cm., 1947 July 16
          On the Italian translation of Elizabethan Essays.
        - 98. Typed letter, signed: London. Two pages, 26cm., 1947 November 21
        - 99. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1948 February 12
        - 100. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26 1/2cm., 1948 June 29
        - 101. Typed letter, signed: Princeton, N. J. One page, 28cm., 1948 November 8
          Impossible to talk to Grolier Club.
        - 102. Typed letter, signed: London. Two pages, 21cm., 1948 December 30
          On the dating of his essays. With typed sheet prepared by DCG with manuscript dates and markings by TSE.
        - 103. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 21cm., 1949 January 24
          On the Magdalene College Sermon.
        - 104. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 21cm., 1949 February 22
          On proof copies.
        - 105. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26cm., 1949 August 10
          Arranging a meeting. With manuscript postscript by Eliot. With typed letter, signed, from secretary, 1949 Aug 15.
        - 106. Typed letter, signed: London. One page, 26cm., 1949 October 19
          On The Undergraduate Poems of T. S. Eliot. With typed letter, signed, from Eliot's secretary Valerie Fletcher (later Mrs. Eliot), 16 Nov 1949.